<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>demistify &amp; simplify tech concepts Blog</title>
        <link>https://nolo28mokgosi@github.io/blog</link>
        <description>demistify &amp; simplify tech concepts Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding Boundaries]]></title>
            <link>https://nolo28mokgosi@github.io/blog/understandingboundaries</link>
            <guid>understandingboundaries</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA["One of the undecided problems of software development is deciding what the boundaries of a piece of software is" - Martin Fowler. This is statement is so true, creeps into most of my design conversation.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&quot;One of the undecided problems of software development is deciding what the boundaries of a piece of software is&quot; - <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ApplicationBoundary.html">Martin Fowler</a>. This is statement is so true, creeps into most of my design conversation. </p><p><img src="/img/blog/boundaries.jpg" alt="Cable Mess"/></p><p><em>Photo by goodtherapy.org</em></p><p>If we step out of tech world for a moment, we&#x27;ll realise that boundaries are applied in our everyday life. Some of those boundaries has unwritten rules or principles.</p><p>Let&#x27;s zoom into John&#x27;s life as an example. John is a 14 year old boy who lives with his parents and younger sister in a 4 bedroom house. He loves football and has posters all over the bedroom he shares with his younger sister. John&#x27;s mother is strict and likes order in her house. John&#x27;s father is chilled. </p><h2>John&#x27;s house</h2><ul><li><p><strong>Bedroom 1:</strong> Parents bedroom, always clean and organised. It is clear that mother&#x27;s standards and principles are followed.</p></li><li><p><strong>Bedroom 2:</strong> A room John shares with his sister. Through constant screaming and ruling with terror, John&#x27;s mother tried to instill her standards and principles and failed dismallly. John implemented his own standard &amp; principles</p></li><li><p><strong>Kitchen &amp; Lounge:</strong> Just like John&#x27;s parents bedroom, always organised. It is clear that mother&#x27;s standards and principles are followed. Kitchen is for cooking. Lounge is where family watches 7de laan everyday at 7. </p></li></ul><p>Looking at this example, and zooming into our everyday life, you will realise our space has boundaries and most of the rules or principles are not written down. For example, only sleep in the bedroom, cook in the kitchen.</p><h2>In Software World</h2><p>In large organisations where teams write software each and every day, it is important to define and document boundaries. Since teams have different stakeholders, you might find teams writing duplicate capabilities in the same organisation. </p><p>Take this example: </p><ul><li>Stakeholder: Can you create a screen where i can manage client data?</li><li>Engineer: Say no more.</li><li>Stakeholder: I would like to send an email to client after completing this task.</li><li>Engineer: I got it, its a simple functionality to build.</li><li>Stakeholder: Can you make sure that I can see all the holidays on the system?</li><li>Engineer: We know what to to build. We&#x27;ll be done next week. </li></ul><p>In this case, tech team is writing software to fulfil stakeholder needs without checking if the capablility exists in the organisation. Since  boundaries are not applied, the team will end up with an application that manages client data, execute client communications &amp; managing holiday data. </p><p>It does not mean it&#x27;s bad to have such application. It&#x27;s only bad if the boundary is not defined, it&#x27;s done in isolation or leads to refactoring and data clean up projects in future. </p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>Defining boundaries in large organisations can be a difficult task but it is a good investment.</p><p> The absence of software or application boundaries leads to</p><ul><li>Data being duplicated &amp; managed in different applications.</li><li>Increase in cost at organisational level</li><li>Bad client experience e.g. where client updates address or contact details and the update does not filter down to other applications</li></ul><p>The results of boundary definition exercise should include this major points:</p><ul><li>Application is responsible for ABC capability/function</li><li>Application is NOT responsible for XYZ capability/function</li></ul><p><a href="https://teamtopologies.com/book">Team Topologies</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215">Domain Driven Design</a> books shines the light in this subject.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Entanglement]]></title>
            <link>https://nolo28mokgosi@github.io/blog/entanglement</link>
            <guid>entanglement</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Imagine you are an engineer working in a application/system that has been operating for years. Your stakeholders asks  to implement a breaking change on the API.Assuming you joined the organisation less than a year ago, you ask around if anyone knows  about your API integration points and no one knows. You start feeling like an application you working on looks and feels like the picture below, "ENTANGLED".]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Imagine you are an engineer working in a application/system that has been operating for years. Your stakeholders asks  to implement a breaking change on the API.Assuming you joined the organisation less than a year ago, you ask around if anyone knows  about your API integration points and no one knows. You start feeling like an application you working on looks and feels like the picture below, &quot;ENTANGLED&quot;.</p><p><img src="./messy-cables.png" alt="Cable Mess"/><br/>
<em>Photo by mikemontague.com</em></p><h2>How do you know your application is entangled?</h2><p>According to cambridge dictionary, entanglement is &quot;a situation or relationship that you are involved in and that is difficult to escape from&quot;. The word was made popular in 2020 by famous couple in the US. In this document, we will discuss entaglement in IT applications. </p><p>The minute you feel like you are diffusing a bomb when you are asked to implement a breaking changes on the API or switch off integration point, know that your application is entagled :smiley:.</p><p><img src="./diffusebomb.jpg" alt="Diffuce bomb"/><br/>
<em>Photo by mikemontague.com</em></p><h2>How to avoid entanglement</h2><ol><li><p><strong>Document current state of your application</strong><br/>
<!-- -->There should be a simple highlevel documentation or design that outlines application integration points. It will also be beneficial to outline users/user groups interacting with the application.</p></li><li><p><strong>Keep you current state of your application alive</strong><br/>
<!-- -->Documenting current state is one thing, keeping documentation alive is always a challenge.
I&#x27;ve worked on <a href="https://c4model.com">C4</a> and love it. It&#x27;s simple, maintainable especially if you focus only at &quot;System Context&quot; for organisation wide designs.</p></li><li><p><strong>Agree to certain format</strong><br/>
<!-- -->Fact is different designers/architects/engineers document differently. There is a chance that most application have documentation somewhere in archives in word documents, wiki of some sort. We might be outdated, or might be difficult to find, or difficult to understand. Choose from formats/frameworks like <a href="https://c4model.com">C4</a> and <a href="https://www.cs.ubc.ca/~gregor/teaching/papers/4+1view-architecture.pdf">4+1</a>) </p></li><li><p><strong>Be clear on design assets of the organisation</strong><br/>
<!-- -->Code in organisation is treated as a first class citizen. Gone are the days where we used to panic when engineer&#x27;s machine crashed and we loose days worth of code. Nowadays our code is in the repo, and we have CI/CD in place.
Just like code where we adhere to certain principles &amp; standandards, it is important to agree on organisation level design assest, and give them first class citizen membership.</p></li><li><p><strong>Current state documenation must be accessible</strong>
Current state provide answers to many questions asked in multiple meetings. Instead or reinventing the wheel or getting right people to answer questions like what are the integration points of the appliction? How do they integrate? Which users interact with the application? It&#x27;s so cool to answer by a link to an up-to-date documentation/design.</p></li></ol><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>One might ask, why do we need to create more documents/design assets if we can read code and have a clear pictures. Statement is valid but it is important to remember that: </p><ul><li>Sometimes we need answers in our finger tips to make decisions</li><li>Applications we are building today will live beyond our time (we might leave the orgnisation, or join other teams)</li><li>Applications you working on is part of the broader eco-system of applications</li><li>It helps to provide basic application information to decision makers, non-techincal community within our organisation</li></ul><p>If you would like to take it to the next level, checkout <a href="https://github.com/ddd-crew/bounded-context-canvas">Bounded Context Canvas</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>